

Susanket Sarkar

Data Scientist

sarkar.susanket@gmail.com • +91-8777856661 • LinkedIN • Github • Kaggle

Summary

Data Scientist with 3+ years of combined internship and full-time experience in building and deploying real-world AI system across image, audio, geospatial and text data, driving efficiency, accuracy, and tangible product impact at scale.

Skills

Python, R, SQL, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, Docker, Git, PowerBI, AWS (S3, SageMaker), Azure, LLM, MLOps

Work Experience

Data Scientist, AEREO, Bengaluru, India

May 2024 - Present

- Built a 3D segmentation model using drone data to detect mining features like haul roads, stockpiles, replacing manual mapping
- Developed models on AWS and Azure AI using Dockerized batch jobs, allowing on-demand scaling across enterprise workloads
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Designed and maintained } \textbf{MLOps} \ \text{pipelines, from training to deployment and monitoring, ensuring reliability, speed in production } \\$
- Created a full Python-based repository for all pre and post-processing steps, including data cleaning, image slicing, from scratch
- Used SQL to build dashboards and metrics so business teams could track model outputs, performance, and validate predictions
- Integrated **OpenAI's GPT-3** into a **natural language dashboard**, allowing users to ask questions and get these translated into **SQL** and spatial queries, enabling intuitive, conversational access to geospatial insights.
- Enabled spatial query support by connecting GPT-3 to PostGIS database, allowing retrieval and analysis of mining infra metrics
- Developed rural infra models detecting rural roads, lakes, trees, wells, poles, and buildings using orthoimages with 96% accuracy
- Automated pipelines via ML, cutting manual digitisation time by 93%, boosting accuracy by 45%, and cutting \$10.8K in ops cost
- Bridged technical gap by crafting metrics and dashboards, enabling **stakeholders** to interpret model insights and validate outputs

Data Science Intern, AEREO, Bengaluru, India

May 2023 - July 2023

- Directed a project for micro-object detection in images, solving business problems through aerial analysis using machine learning
- Managed a vast 3TB photogrammetry dataset sourced from 150 distinct vendors, streamlining data organization and storage
- \bullet Developed a MXNet model with 92% precision and drove automation, saving Rs. 10L in annual expenses and 40 weekly hrs
- Integrated advanced features into Aereo's B2B SaaS Analytics; uplifting the Platform Adoption Rate by 27%, increasing growth

Data Science Intern, Fitbuddy, Bengaluru, India

Sept 2022 - Nov 2022

- Leveraged Python's OpenCV & MediaPipe libraries to form logic of a Body Pose Detection Model enabling body pose detection
- Formed relational matrices by considering landmark relationships and trained the system on Naive Bayes, SVM, Random Forests
- \bullet Refined and optimized codebase to detect exercises accurately, adding functionalities for yoga poses, obtaining an 87% F1 Score
- $\bullet \ \, \text{Integrated the feature to production, resulting in a 20% increase in application downloads due to superior pose detection UX }$

Data Science Intern, Vitt.AI

January 2023 – March 2023

- Automated a system that transcribed and translated **18 hrs** of speech data from 10 languages from customer service conversation Utilized MFCC (Mel Frequency Cepstral Coefficients) for audio feature extraction, preparing data for transcription and translation
- Finetuned Whisper model on audio data, achieving a Word Error Rate (WER) of <19, translating conversations to English.
- The pipeline witnessed an increase in efficiency by 15%, automating tasks and saving 27 hours in language processing endeavors.

Data Science Intern, Kincare

July 2022 – September 2022

- Engineered and deployed a data pipeline for an in-app chatbot, facilitating users to upload and query their PDF medical reports
- Developed dashboard and visualizations using Power BI, showing 30+ vital KPIs and providing insights to business stakeholders
- Automated 10+ tasks leading to 52% reduction in analysis time, streamlining the process to solve the business problems efficiently

Projects and Research Work

Optimising Latent Representations in VAE (Supervisor: Prof. S. P. Pal, IIT Kharagpur)

Jan. 2024 – Apr. 2024

Built a VAE-LSTM framework on battery datasets to test denoised latent representations; improved prediction accuracy by 30%, achieving an R² of 0.93, proving constrained latent spaces can enhance sequence learning and extract robust temporal patterns.

Explainable Deep Learning for Heart Sound Analysis (Supervisor: Prof. S. P. Pal, IIT Kharagpur) Aug. 2023 – Dec. 2023 Designed an explainable deep learning pipeline for cardiac disease detection using a fusion of auditory features and fine-tuned models; achieved 99.1% accuracy, ensuring transparency through interpretable visualizations (LIME, Shapely) and decision paths.

Real Time Forest Fire Detection (Supervisor: Prof V. Rachella, IIT Kharagpur)

May 2022 - August 2022

Developed a forest fire detection system using a custom ResNet50 pipeline trained on 25K images; achieved 92% accuracy and 87% F1 score, integrated alert system via SMTP, and successfully flagged 3 live fires, enabling early intervention and hazard control.

Competitions

Ranked 7/5255 at Trilytics '23 (IIM-C): Built an 87%-accurate risk prediction system & dashboard to forecast mining accidents and business impact.

Won Cisco Convolve '23 (1/1500): Built an inventory demand predictor and management system using SARIMAX & Prophet, reducing SMAPE by **23%** and forecasting a year ahead.

Education

Bachelor of Technology, Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur

Nov 2020 – April 2024

GPA - 8.06/10

Major: Aerospace Engineering (Specialization in Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning)
Relevant Coursework:

- Statistics for AI/ML: Sampling, Mixture Models, Hypothesis Test, Reinforcement Learning, Causal Inference
- Machine Learning: Bayesian Theory, Decision Tree, Ensembles, Support Vector, Dimensionality Reduction, Perceptron, CNN, RNN